Suchismit **Mahapatra**

Amobee Research, Redwood City, CA 94063

□716-435-8865 | Suchismi@buffalo.edu | # https://schrilax.github.io/ | I suchismit | 🚟 schrilaxs | 🔞 suchismit

About Me __

I am a Research Scientist with Amobee, applying different Machine/Deep Learning and NLP techniques to solve related problems. I completed my PhD with the Machine Learning & Data Science Research group at University of Buffalo. I have 7+ years of research and 5 years of developer experience during which I have been exposed and worked on a variety of problems.

Research Interests

My research focuses on designing and implementing novel algorithms which enable large-scale learning and includes:

- Machine/Deep Learning
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Deep Graph/Geometric Learning
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

Academic Background _____

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

April 2012 - June 2018

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data. 🚨 🔁
- Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript)

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

Buffalo, NY

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

- Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity.
- Advisor: Rohini Srihari | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 | Department rank: 1 out of 555 (Transcript)

National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India August 2001 - May 2005

September 2010 - June 2012

B.Tech. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

- Specialization: Discrete Mathematics and Algorithms
- Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with Honors)(Transcript) | Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

Honors _

2021	Became a reviewer for EMNLP 2021, ACL 2021 and NeurIPS 2021.	Sunnyvale, CA
2020	Became a reviewer for ICML 2021 and ICLR 2021.	Sunnyvale, CA
2020	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Theory of Reinforcement Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2019	Became a reviewer for ICML 2020.	Palo Alto, CA
2019	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2017	Won a NSF Junior Researcher Award to attend CBMS Conference on Sparse Recovery.	Las Cruces, NM
2016	Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator.	Santa Clara, CA
2015	Won a NSF Student Travel Award to attend IEEE Big Data 2015.	Santa Clara, CA
2013	Won a rare Research Assistant-ship covering my second year as a Masters student.	Buffalo, NY
2004	Scored 99 percentile in Zonal, Discipline and National categories of National IT Aptitude Test.	Rourkela, India
2004	Subsequently won a Bhavishya Jyoti Scholarship for above.	Rourkela, India

Skills & Proficiencies ____

Python | PyTorch | C/C++ | TensorFlow | Apache MapReduce | Scala | CUDA | Hive

Research Experience _____

Amobee Research Redwood City, CA

SCIENTIST I

- March 2020 Present • Developed a novel bidding strategy based on Win Price (WP) estimation
 - Developed and productionized a novel bidding strategy using nonlinear ML based approaches for estimating WP.
- Built a Factorization Machine (FM) based ML pipeline
 - Led efforts to build a FM based ML pipeline for usage in production.

MAY 1, 2021

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

July 2018 - December 2019

- Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Enhanced existing production Click-through and Sales prediction pipeline using nonlinear ML techniques. Improved stability of our new models significantly from +50% to +5%. A/B test using new models resulted in +3-6% uplift in long-term RexT on all platforms.
- Theoretical aspects on Deep Learning (working with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.
- Resolving the posterior-collapse issue in Seq2Seq learning
 - Developed quantization based approaches towards resolving the posterior-collapse issue.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2018 - May 2018

- The Research Foundation for Solvi
- Parallelized Hierarchical Clustering (worked with Haimonti Dutta)
 - Worked towards developing a novel parallel hierarchical clustering algorithm using activization strategies.
- Kernel Manifold Learning (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed novel Manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes. 📙

Criteo Research

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

September 2017 - December 2017

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

- Efficient Domain Adaptation (worked with Suju Rajan)
 - Understanding how to efficiently deal with the Domain Adaptation problem via Optimal Transportation.

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling using Adversarial Transfer Learning (worked with Suju Rajan)
 - Tried to learn a robust QP model across retailer domains using Adversarial Transfer Learning. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2017 - May 2017

May 2017 - August 2017

- Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (worked with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)
 - Interpreting complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🔼 🛗 🛗
- Incorporating complex constraints for sparse Logistic Regression (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Worked towards solving the sparse Logistic Regression problem with hierarchical tree-based constraints.

BD Biosciences San Jose, CA

MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM DESIGN INTERN

June 2016 - August 2016

June 2013 - December 2015

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
 - Upscaled BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x. 🔼 🚨

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (worked with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)
 - Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting. 📙
- Social Network Modeling (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed the xKPGM model for social network modeling. 🔼
- \cdot Variance Reduction techniques in Distributed Optimization (worked with Haimonti Dutta / Varun Chandola)
- Worked towards developing novel variance reduction techniques for the ERM problem.
- Understanding Rumor Propagation in Social Networks (worked with Shambhu Upadhyaya / Varun Chandola)
 - Worked towards modeling rumor propagation in social networks.
- Volcanic Flow Prediction (worked with Abani Patra / Varun Chandola / Paul Bauman)
 - Developed a novel Gaussian Process based model for prediction of flow using GPGPUs.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

June 2011 - August 2012

- Localization via Entropy Reduction (worked with Robert Platt)
 - Developed a novel active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS. 🔁 🛗

Publications

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Efficient Graph Similarity Computation via Optimal Transport. Khoa Doan, Saurav Manchanda, Suchismit Mahapatra and Chandan Reddy. (To appear in SIGIR 2021)
- 2. Discretized Bottleneck in VAE: Posterior-Collapse-Free Sequence-to-Sequence Learning. Yang Zhao, Ping Yu, **Suchismit Mahapatra**, Qinliang Su and Changyou Chen. 2020 (Under submission)

- 3. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. 2019 (Under submission)
- 4. S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017
- 5. Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra**, Frank Schoeneman, Varun Chandola, Jaroslaw Zola, Nils Napp. Proceedings of SIAM Data Mining Conference, 2017
- 6. Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.

Additional Certifications/Projects _____

- NLP certification from NVIDIA Deep Learning Institute 🚨
- Machine Learning course offered by Stanford under Andrew Ng 🚨
- Implemented 3PRR Parallel Chain and PRRR Serial Chain Manipulators under Venkat Krovi 日日
- Developed ElGooG A search engine using ~100000 TREC documents as corpus (won the NTipS 2010 competition) 🔀

Teaching _____

- Taught a course on Classification and Decision Trees [Q4 2018, Q2 2019, Q4 2019] while at Criteo Research.
- Taught a course on Generative Models [Q2 2019, Q4 2019] while at Criteo Research.

Seminar/Symposia _____

2017	S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. (IEEE Big Data 2017) 📙	Boston, NY
2017	Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (SIAM SDM 2017) 🔼	Houston, TX
2016	Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (UB Computer Science Mixer) 🕒	Buffalo, NY
2016	Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry Data via Adaptive Mean Shift. (BD Biosciences) 🚨 🔼	San Jose, CA
2015	Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. (IEEE Big Data 2015) 🔼	Santa Clara, CA
2012	Entropy-based localization framework for localizing known objects. (NEMS 2012) 🛗	Bedford, MA